Guide to the J. B. Matthews Papers, 1862-1986 and undated
J. B. Matthews papers 1862-1986 and undated
- Research Correspondence Series, circa 1930s-1960s., (39 boxes)
  - Spivak, Lawrence E., 1953
  - Spolansky, Jake, 1951, 1953& undated
  - Stanley, Welles R., 1953
  - Starr, C.C., 1953-1956& undated
  - Steele, Walter S., 1934-1960
  - Stolberg, Benjamin, 1939-1951& undatedIncluded are photographs
  - Stolberg, David, 1946-1956
  - Stringfellow, George E., 1953, 1954
  - Sullivan, Paul J., 1953
  - Surine, Donald A., 1950-1957
  - Survey, 1963
  - Sweany, Donald I., Jr., 1957-1962
  - T -, 1950-1961 (Box 682)
  - Talmadge, Herman E., 1957, 1959
  - Television Programs, 1953
  - Tenney, Jack B., 1946-1950
  - Thomas, Parnell, 1950-1959
  - Thurmond, Strom, 1960-1963
  - Tishman, Maurice, 1954
  - Time Inc., 1948-1969
  - Timken Roller Bearing Company, 1951
  - Ton, Hollington R., 1957
  - Torn, Roland S., 1953
  - Twentieth Century Fox Film Corp., 1953
  - Utley, Freda, 1947-1963& undated
  - V -, 1953-1962
  - Van Marter, Donald D., 1954-1961
  - Velde, Harold H., 1952& undated
  - Viereck, George Sylvester, 1954, 1955
  - Von Boeselager, Bea, 1953-1958& undated
  - Von Mises, Ludwig, 1950-1967& undated
  - Von Wedelstaedt, Corrinne, 1951-1955
  - W -, 1951-1962& undated (Box 683)
  - WMCA, 1953
  - WPIX, 1951
  - Waldman, Louis, 1951-1967
  - Waldrop, Frank L., 1950, 1952
  - Walter, Francis, E., 1956-1963
  - Ward, Stuart R., 1954
  - Ware, Richard A., 1957-1963
  - Waring, Thomas R., 1958& undated
  - Warner, William E., 1953-1965
  - Watt, Robert W., 1953
  - Weitinger, Mrs. J.C., 1955
  - Welch, Robert H.W., Jr., 1954-1960
  - Welch, Robert, H.W., Jr., 1961-1964& undated (Box 685)
  - Welker, Herman, 1954-1956
  - Western, Irene, 1955
  - Wever, Ned, 1953-1958& undated
  - White, C.M., 1955
  - Whitney, Lloyd, 1953, 1954
  - Widener, Alice, 1953-1961& undated
  - Wilcox, Edward B., 1947-1955& undated
  - Wilkie, Lloyd, 1962, 1963
  - Willebrandt, Mabel Walker, 1953
  - William Volker Charities Fund, 1952-1953(June)
  - William Volker Charities Fund, 1953(July)-1962 (Box 686)
  - Willoughby, Charles A., 1954-1958& undated
  - Wilson, Donald R., 1953
  - Wittfogel, Karl A., 1950-1954
  - Wittmer, Felix, 1952-1955
  - Woltman, Frederick, 1935-1957& undated Photograph
  - Woman's Day, 1949-1961
  - Y -, 1955-1958
  - Youth Wants to Know, 1953
  - Z -, 1954-1963
- Benjamin Mandel Series, 1920-1970, (7 boxes) (Box 687-693)
  Papers of Mandel, one-time Director of Research for the U.S. Senate Judiciary Committee's Subcommittee on Internal Security. Major categories include subjects; general papers; correspondence (primarily between Mandel and Matthews); clippings sorted by decades; and volumes.
  - Subjects:
    - Anti-Communist Bureau, 1923-1946 (Box 687)
    - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace:
      - General Papers, 1959-1968
      - Annual Reports, 1958-1964
    - Communist Party and the United Front, 1935-1938
    - Dies Committee, 1942
    - E.P. Dutton and Company, Inc., Publishers, 1935-1940& undated
    - Fascist Groups, 1940-1942
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation:
      - General Papers, 1947-1955
      - General Papers, 1956-1970& undated (Box 688)
      - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1937-1952
    - Gitlow, Benjamin, 1939-1943& undated (Box 689)
    - Government Employees, 1941-1950
    - Index of Photographs in The Daily Worker, 1922-1942
    - National Anti-War Congress, 1938
    - National Review, 1955-1956
    - People's Press. Inc., 1939-1944& undated
    - Philadelphia County Board Department of Public Assistance, 1942
    - Reviewing Board of the Philadelphia County Board of Assistance, Stenographic Report of Hearing, Nov. 24-26, 1941& Dec. 6, 18, 1941(pp. 55-656)
    - Reviewing Board of the Philadelphia County Board of Assistance, Stenographic Report of Hearing, Dec. 20, 1941& Jan. 7, 1942(pp. 657-858) (Box 690)
    - Reviewing Board of the Philadelphia County Board of Assistance, Commonwealth's Requests, ca. 1942
    - Roosevelt Administration:
      - General Papers, 1939-1941& undated
      - Writings, undated
    - Russian Courses, undated
    - Technocracy, undated
    - Trojan Horse in Government, undated
  - General Papers, 1920-1968 (Box 691)
  - General Papers, undated (Box 692)
  - Correspondence between Matthews and Mandel, 1939-1969& undated
  - Clippings:
    - General, 1940s-1950's & undated (Box 693)
    - Excerpts from The Congressional Record, 1945-1947, 1949-1953
    - Pro-War, 1937& undated
    - French, 1937& undated- Andrew Smith
    - German, undated
  - Volumes:
    - Case Studies in Personnel Security, August, 1955
    - Scrapbook of Clippings
    - The Soviet World Outlook, undated
- Motion Pictures and Television Series, 1945-1960, (2 boxes)
  Topical arrangement, containing a file of correspondence, and information pertaining to several Hollywood figures, communism, and a film, My Son John.
  - Blankfort, Michael, 1951 (Box 694)
  - Blaustein, Julian, 1952
  - Cohn, Art, 1952
  - Communism in the Motion Picture Industry, 1960
  - Fay, Frank vs. Actors Equity Association, 1945-1946
  - Hartnett, Vincent, 1949-1967
  - Hollywood Letters, A-D
  - Hollywood Letters, E-Z (Box 695)
  - Hollywood Letters (American Legion), 1952-1953
  - Hollywood Letters (American Legion Magazine,) 1952
  - Levenson, Sam, 1952
  - Michael, Sandra, 1953
  - My Son John Film, 1945-1952
  - Sherman, Vincent, 1952
- Personal Files Series, 1895-1970, (10 boxes)
  Principally information relating to Matthews' private life and his family. The major categories are subjects, telephone listings, telephone messages, clippings, pictures, and general papers.
  - Subjects:
    - Affair of the Batavia Police, 1921 (Box 696)
    - American Aeronaut, 1943-1965
    - Biographical, 1963-1967
    - Burd, Johnny and Margaret, 1952-1961
    - Clements, John A., 1941-1962
    - Clergy Incident, 1952-1953,July
    - Clergy Incident, 1953, July (Box 697)
    - Committee on the Judiciary (Scope of Soviet Activity in the United States, Part 3), 1959
    - Cressman, Grace Matthews, 1951-1963
    - Dressel and Altman, 1966
    - Hopkinsville New Ear, 1953
    - Latin America Trip, 1958
    - Leigh, W. Colston, 1937-1938
    - Matthews, John E., 1951-1963
    - Matthews, Joseph, Jr., 1951-1960 (Box 698)
    - Matthews, Martin, 1950-1970
    - Matthews, Roy and Genevieve, 1944-1963
    - Matthews Quits McCarthy Committee, 1953-1960
    - Maynard, Ruth E. (Shallcross) Matthews, 1950-1963
    - Mote, Carl H., 1939 (Box 699)
    - National Exchange Clubs, 1951-1953
    - National Society of New England Women, 1952-1954
    - Palyi, Melchior, 1954-1969
    - Radio Broadcasts, 1950-1951
    - Recordings, 1952
    - Rudd, Augustin G., 1957-1967
    - Scarborough, Dorothy Fitzpatrick, 1962-1963
    - The Shield, 1947
    - Sikes, Jesse and Walter, 1953-1963
    - Testimonial Dinner, 1952-1953 (Box 700)
    - Todt, George H., 1954-1955
    - Twentieth Anniversary, 1934-1955
  - Telephone Listings, 1942
  - Telephone Messages, 1949-1951
  - Telephone Messages, 1952-1955 (Box 701)
  - Clippings, 1934-1951
  - Clippings, 1953-1966 (Box 702)
  - Pictures, 1895-1961& undated
  - Pictures (Negatives and Slides), 1961& undated
  - General Papers, 1915-1954,May (Box 703)
  - General Papers, 1954, June-1968& undated (Box 704)
  - General Papers, undated (Box 705)
- Ruth I. Matthews Series, 1930-1986., (6 boxes)
  Relates to the personal career and life of Ruth I. Matthews, third wife of J.B. Matthews. Alphabetical correspondence, subjects, and general papers are the major categories.
  - Alphabetical Correspondence:
    - A, 1944-1948 (Box 705)
    - American Association for Public Opinion Research, 1947-1948
    - B. 1945-1948
    - Bain, Read, 1940-1945
    - Bassett, Raymond, 1947-1948
    - Breen, Joseph, 1943-1947
    - Bryn Mawr College, 1936-1948
    - C, 1940-1947
    - Childs, Harwood, 1940-1946
    - Curtis Study, 1947-1948
    - D-E, 1942-1947
    - Dodd, Stuart and Beirut, 1945-1947
    - F. 1940-1948 (Box 706)
    - Facey, Paul, 1930-1948
    - Farrar and Rinehart, 1944-1946
    - G. 1943-1944
    - Goldwyn and Farnol, 1946-1947
    - H. 1940-1947
    - I-K, 1938-1948
    - L, 1940-1948
    - La Piere, Richard, 1940-1948
    - Lazarsfeld, Paul, 1940-1944
    - Ludeke, Herbert C., 1940-1947
    - M, 1936-1948
    - MGM, 1945-1946
    - Mohalen, Felix, 1944-1948
    - Moreno, J.L., 1940-1947
    - Mother (Mrs. Inglis), 1947
    - N-O, 1940-1948 (Box 707)
    - National Board of Review, 1944-1946
  - Subjects:
    - Combat, 1965-1970
    - Constructive Action, Inc., 1963-1966
    - Cressman Service, 1965-1966
    - Deadline Data on World Affairs, 1957-1960
    - Edmonds, Richard W., 1968
    - Genocide Convention, 1961-1971
    - Grave-side Service for J.B. Matthews, 1966 (Box 708)
    - Letters from Family, 1966-1967
    - Letters of Condolence, 1966
    - McCarthy, Joseph R., 1965-1967
    - Parkinson's Disease, 1957-1963
    - Periodicals: Buying and Selling, 1959-1962
    - Religious Publications, 1954
    - Social Security Question, 1971
    - Subscription Renewals, 1968
    - University of Oregon and University of Wyoming, 1966-1968
    - William Volker Fund, 1962-1969
  - General Papers, 1939-1968 (Box 709)
  - General Papers, 1969-1986& undated (Box 710)
- General Correspondence Series, 1917-1981., (2 boxes)
  Letters, telegrams, memoranda, and petitions that came to the library loose with much other miscellaneous material. These items were pulled together into this series using a chronological arrangement. Many of the letters are copies and pertain to organizations about which Matthews seemed to be interested in collecting information. Usually the correspondence is either addressed to someone other than Matthews, or bears a general greeting such as Dear friend, sir, citizen, brother, or member.
  - Papers, 1917-1949 (Box 710)
  - Papers, 1949-1981 (Box 711)
- Addresses and Writings Series, 1862-1973., (13 boxes)
  Primarily contains articles and speeches, but also reports, statements, notes, lecture contracts, and memoranda. Also, there is correspondence, especially concerning arrangements for lectures and responses to articles. Principally these are the works of Matthews, but this series also encompasses Ruth I. Matthews and others; some of the writings are unidentified. Formats include originals, reprints, mimeographed copies, and clippings. The two major categories are the alphabetical series and the general papers. The alphabetical series, the largest section, is organized by title, topic, or place of speech.
  - Alphabetical:
    - America is Losing the War on Communism, 1953 (Box 712)
    - The American Adventure, undated
    - America's Town Meeting of the Air, 1939
    - Amnesty for Adlai, 1956
    - An Anti-Communist's Guide to Action, 1954
    - Ax-Grinders, 1963
    - The Big Lie - A Documented Story, undated
    - Blake, Eugene Carson, 1954-1955
    - Byblos: The World's Oldest Living Town, 1955
    - Carib Report 7: Monopoly II, 1944-1950
    - Caribbean Cancer, 1950
    - Castro, Fidel: International Terrorist, 1957-1959
    - Castro, Fidel: Review of, 1959
    - Catholics, 1953-1954
    - Chicago Speech, 1954 (Box 713)
    - Chicago Speech, 1959
    - Chinese Communist Party Influence on Latin America Communist Parties, 1957
    - Cincinnati Speech, 1957
    - Civil Liberties, undated
    - Clean Comic Books for Children, 1955
    - Collingswood, N.J. Speech, 1958
    - Communism and the Churches, 1961
    - Communism and the Colleges, 1953 (Box 714)
    - Communist Fronts, 1949-1958
    - Communists and Children, 1949
    - Communists and the New Deal, 1953
    - Communists, Negroes and Integration, undated
    - Crisis in the Western Hemisphere, 1960 (Box 715)
    - Davis, Elmer, 1943-1954
    - Dru, Philip, 1944-1963
    - Education and Communism, 1952
    - The Filter System, Monopoly I, 1957
    - Flanders of Vermont, undated (Box 716)
    - Fund for the Republic, 1955
    - Furstenwalde, H.C., 1965
    - Garden City Speech, 1956
    - Germany and the East-West Crisis, 1959
    - Harding College Speech, 1957
    - Headquarters of Subversion, 1954
    - Hollywood, 1947-1952
    - Holy Alliance - Myths and Movements, 1958
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1954-1955 (Box 717)
    - Hunter College Speech, 1955
    - Hutchins, Hysteria and Humbug, 1953-1956
    - Immigration, 1952-1963
    - Introduction to Economic History, undated
    - Khrushchev's Visit, 1959
    - Lamb, Edward, undated
    - Let's Defend the Western Hemisphere, undated
    - Look Magazine, 1953-1954
    - Los Angeles Speech, 1954
    - Los Angeles Speech, 1956
    - Lohman, Clarence, 1953-1954 (Box 718)
    - The Lost Continent, 1959
    - Loyalty of Government Clerks, 1862
    - McCarthy, Joe - Is He Right or Wrong?, 1954
    - Men and Mentalities, undated
    - Mercury's Opinion, 1955
    - Milwaukee Speech, 1956
    - The Monopoly I, undated
    - Moscow's Medicine Men, 1953
    - The Myth, 1958
    - National Council of Civic Responsibility, 1964-1965 (Box 719)
    - National Review, 1960
    - The New Class, 1950-1958
    - The Old Testament, 1924-1926
    - Omaha Speech, Nov., 1956
    - Oppenheimer, Robert J., Dr., 1958
    - Peace, 1955
    - The Prize is Africa, 1955
    - Rabbi Schultz' Testimonial Dinner, 1955 (Box 720)
    - Red Fire in Politics, 1933
    - Red Infiltration of Theological Seminaries, 1953
    - Reds and the Churches, 1953-1958
    - Relief for American Reds, 1957
    - Reuther, Walter, 1957
    - Rotary International, 1957
    - Senators, Too, Are Susceptible, undated
    - Sentner, David, 1946
    - So Big, undated
    - Social Education, 1957-1958
    - Subversion in the Foundations, 1957
    - Symington, Stuart W., undated
    - Tactics of the Communist Offensive in Latin America, 1953 (Box 721)
    - Television: A Mixed Blessing, 1948-1954
    - This is Artukovic, undated
    - Torch of Liberty, 1959
    - UNESCO, 1955
    - UNESCO: Three Cents' Worth of Poison, undated
    - United Nations, 1949-1952
    - Vanguard in Guatemala--The Myth Comes to America, undated (Box 722)
    - War Propaganda, 1939
    - The What and How of Communist Fronts, 1955
    - What's Ahead for the American Negro Under Desegregation, 1954-1955
    - The White House Sets the Pace, 1953
    - World Affairs and U.S. Foreign Policy, 1960
    - World Council of Churches, 1954
    - The World Health Organization, undated
    - Worldwide Communist Apparatus for Scientists, 1954
    - The Years of Betrayal, 1954
    - Your Job and Your Pay, undated
  - General Papers, 1928-1934
  - General Papers, 1936-1973& undated (Box 723)
  - General Papers, undated (Box 724)
- Clippings Series, 1930s-1980s., (6 boxes)
  Originals and photocopies, primarily from newspapers but some from periodicals. The categories are general, civil rights, labor and unions, and Vietnam. Clippings are organized by decades within these categories.
  - General, 1930s-1940s (Box 725)
  - General, 1950s (Box 726)
  - General, 1950s-1960s (Box 727)
  - General, 1960s (Box 728)
  - General, 1970s-1980s& undated (Box 729)
  - Civil Rights, 1940s-1970s
  - Labor and Unions, 1940s-1950s, 1963,& undated (Box 730)
  - Vietnam, 1960s-1970s
- Printed Material Series, 1916-1983., (5 boxes)
  Originally unorganized mimeographed and printed items that were grouped together. Although of a general nature, the papers pertain to left-wing, Communist, and right-wing organizations. Subdivisions of the series are pamphlets and leaflets, serials, and press releases. A group of general papers includes statements, reprints, flyers, general announcements and invitations for various programs and events, resolutions, etc.
  - General Papers, 1927-1983 and undated (Box 731)
  - Pamphlets and Leaflets, 1926-1983& undated (Box 732)
  - Serials: (Box 733)
    - Arthur Gaeth Reports on Unemployment, Numbers 1-13
    - Citizens Informer, 1974-1975
    - Confidential Report, 1949
    - Council Against Communist Aggression, 1971-1972
    - Digest of Current Communist Activities, 1956-1957
    - The Herald of Freedom, 1972
    - The Individualist, 1938-1939
    - La Wisp, 1969-1971
    - National Republic Lettergram, Numbers 169-235
    - News from American Society for Russian Relief, Inc., 1945
    - Searchlight, Numbers 1-5
    - Semi-Weekly Digest of U.K. News and Activities, 1951
    - Statements and Speeches, 1983
    - U.E. on the Air! featuring Arthur Gaeth, Numbers 102-140
    - The Westchester Spotlight, 1955-1963
  - Serials: (Box 734)
    - General, 1916-1983& undated
  - Press Releases, 1941-1969& undated
  - Press Releases and other papers of William E. Jenner, 1938-1963& undated (Box 735)
- Volumes Series, 1918-1970., (7 boxes)
  Primarily printed, typed and mimeographed volumes, such as books, reports, statements, memoranda, lists of persons and their activities, a directory, a manual, a bibliography, and hearings. Some items are organized chronologically.
  - Volumes, 1918-1941 (Box 736)
  - Volumes, 1941 (Box 737)
  - Volumes, 1944-1953 (Box 738)
  - Volumes, 1955-1958 (Box 739)
  - Volumes, 1958-1960 (Box 740)
  - Volumes, 1961-1970 (Box 741)
  - Volumes, undated (Box 742)
  - Buckley, William F., ca. 1966-1985 (Box 743)
    Material pertaining to Buckley, including correspondence, clippings, and printed material.
    [Restriction lifted in 1990 according to contract.]
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1972 Phonotape
- Oversize Material, 1931-1965., (9 folders)
  Items which were pulled from other series to be stored flat in large drawers. These large items are in a fragile or deteriorating condition. Included are papers from the following series: Vertical Files, Personal, Printed Material, and Clippings.
  - Personal Series
    - 1953 and undated (Opaperfolder 9)
  - Printed Material Series
    - Press Releases, 1932 (Opaperfolder 7)
    - General, 1932, 1950 (Oversize-box 788)
    - Broadsides, undated (Oversize-box 788)
  - Printed Material Series
    - Periodicals 1938-1965 (Oversize-box 788)
  - Clippings Series
    - 1936-1959 (Oversize-box 788, Opaperfolder 5)
  - Vertical Files Series
    - American League Against War and Fascism, 1943 (Opaperfolder 6)
    - Mesa Educator, 1946
    - Miami Daily News, 1949
    - Morning Freiheit, 1945 (Opaperfolder 8)
    - Moscow Daily News and Moscow News, 1931-1932
    - Workers Alliance of America, Issues of Work, 1939-1940
  - Vertical Files Series
    - Communism, 1934 (Issues of The Militant) (Oversize-box 788)
  - Vertical Files Series
    - 1930-1950 (Opaperfolder 1, Opaperfolder 5)
- Card Files Series, undated, 43 boxes (boxes 744-787)
  Comprised primarily of name files. The major files are the J.B. Matthews File and the Donald Sweany File. Other files are Titles of Publications, Tocsin, In Process, Miscellaneous, and 4 X 6 Cards.
  - Donald I. Sweany File
    - AAB-BROU (Box 744)
    - BROW-COO (Box 745)
    - COP-ED (Box 746)
    - EE-GD (Box 747)
    - GE-GYZ (Box 748)
    - Arizona, Arkansas, California :: Conn., Del., D.C. (Box 748)
    - Georgia, Hawaii, Idaho, Illinois Indiana, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana :: Michigan (Box 749)
    - A-Z and cards to be filed (Box 749)
    - HAA-HER (Box 750)
    - HES-JOS (Box 751)
    - JOU-LAZ (Box 752)
    - LE-MAZ (Box 753)
    - MEA-NFF (Box 754)
    - NI-NEW YORK (Z) (Box 755)
    - NORTH CAROLINA-PRASC (Box 756)
    - PRASK-SCHUP (Box 757)
    - SCHUR-SZY (Box 758)
    - TAN-WILE (Box 759)
    - WILF-ZIER (Box 760)
    - A-BED (Box 760)
    - BEE-L (Box 761)
    - M-XYZ (Box 762)
  - J.B. Matthews File
    - AA-ATK (Box 763)
    - ATL-BERNK (Box 764)
    - BERNS-BROB (Box 765)
    - BROW-CHAUN (Box 766)
    - CHAUV-CZU (Box 767)
    - DAA-DRA (Box 768)
    - DRE-FELT (Box 769)
    - FEM-GARDI (Box 770)
    - GARDN-GRAH (Box 771)
    - GRAI-HART (Box 772)
    - HARTD-HY (Box 773)
    - IA-KEL (Box 774)
    - KEM-LAR (Box 775)
    - LAS-MAC (Box 776)
    - MAC-MEY (Box 777)
    - MEY-NIS (Box 778)
    - NIT-PEST (Box 779)
    - PET-RDE (Box 780)
    - RE-ROSEN (Box 781)
    - ROSEP-SCHR (Box 782)
    - SCHT-SMITH, T.J. (Box 783)
    - SMITH, T.P.-SZY (Box 784)
    - TA-VY (Box 785)
    - WAA-WILT (Box 786)
    - WIM-ZYG (Box 787)